The extraordinary life story of Ray Charles.
Ray is a drama, music film directed by Taylor Hackford.
Born on a sharecropping plantation in Northern
Florida, Ray Charles went blind at seven.
Inspired by a fiercely independent mom who insisted he make his own way,
He found his calling and his gift behind a piano keyboard.
Touring across the Southern musical circuit, the soulful singer gained a reputation and then
exploded with worldwide fame when he pioneered coupling gospel and country together.
Ray Charles, played by Jamie Foxx.
Della Bea Robinson, played by Kerry Washington.
Margie Hendricks, played by Regina King.
Joe Adams, played by Harry Lennix.
Jeff Brown, played by Clifton Powell.
Fathead Newman, played by Bokeem Woodbine.
Ray is a 2004 American biographical drama film focusing on 30
years in the life of soul musician Ray Charles.
The independently produced film was co-produced and directed
by Taylor Hackford; it was written by James L.
White from a story by Hackford and White.
It stars Jamie Foxx as Charles, along with Kerry Washington, Clifton Powell, Harry Lennix,
Terrence Howard, Larenz Tate, Richard Schiff, and Regina King in supporting roles.
Along with Hackford, the film was also produced by Stuart
Benjamin, Howard Baldwin, and Karen Baldwin.
Ray was released on October 29, 2004, by Universal Pictures.
It received generally positive reviews from critics, with particular praise for Foxx's performance and
became a box office success, grossing $124 million worldwide on a budget of $40 million.
Ray received many accolades and nominations and was nominated in six categories at the 77th Academy
Awards, including Best Picture, and won two: Best Actor for Foxx and Best Sound Mixing.
Foxx also won Best Actor at the Golden Globe, BAFTA, Screen Actors Guild, and Critics' Choice
becoming the second actor to win all five major lead actor awards for the same performance.
Charles had planned to attend a screening of the completed film but died of
liver disease in June 2004, four months prior to the premiere.
The film explores themes of blindness and impaired vision,
country music, jazz, loss of loved one, overdose.
The tone is emotional.